Register of the Harold H. Fisher Papers 1917-1974
Hoover Institution Archives
Harold H. Fisher papers
1917-1974
XX235
Fisher, Harold H., 1890-1975
33 manuscript boxes, 44 card file boxes, 5 envelopes, 1 oversize box, l phonorecord (36.3 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Clippings, printed matter, notes, correspondence, pamphlets, articles, microfilm, and photographs, relating to the Soviet Union, the San Francisco Conference organizing the United Nations, the Civil War in Spain, Herbert Hoover and the American Relief Administration, and the history of Finland.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.; American Relief Administration.; United Nations Conference on International Organization (1945: San Francisco, Calif.); International relief.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1914-1918--Civilian relief.; Finland.; Finland--History.; Spain.; Spain--History--Civil War, 1936-1939.; Soviet Union.; Russia (Federation); Soviet Union--History.; United States--Foreign relations.
Biographical Note
1911 A.B., University of Vermont
1917-1918 Captain of field artillery, U.S. Army
1922 Assistant to Herbert Hoover with the American Relief Administration (A.R.A.); chief of history department of A.R.A.
1936 Honorary doctorate of humane letters (L.H.D.), University of Vermont
1943-1955 Director, Hoover Institution on War, Revolution and Peace; professor of history, Stanford University
1945 Assistant to former governor Harold E. Stassen of U.S. Delegation to San Francisco Conference
1946-1947 Director, School of Naval Administration, Stanford University
1955-1960 Professor of international relations, San Francisco State College
Also: Author of numerous books on the Soviet Union; editorial writer for the Washington Herald; business editor of The New Republic; radio news analyst for CBS and NBC; active in Asian scholarship; former director of Belgian-American Educational Foundation
Scope and Content of Collection
Clippings, printed matter, notes, correspondence, pamphlets, articles, microfilm, and photographs, relating to the Soviet Union, the San Francisco Conference organizing the United Nations, the Civil War in Spain, Herbert Hoover and the American Relief Administration, and the history of Finland.
Container List
- Subject File, 1917-1974 (Box No. 1-20. printed)
  Newspaper clippings, magazines, printed matter, pamphlets, correspondence, manuscripts of books, notes, scripts for lectures and radio broadcasts, and bulletins, arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Africa (Box 1.)
    - General, 1952-1959
    - North Africa, 1951-1956
  - Allen, Henry J., "Senator Allen Looks Into the Real Russia," clippings of a series of articles for the New York Evening Post, 1933
  - Argentina, 1945-1955
  - Armstrong, John A., "History of the C.P.S.U.," n.d. Mimeographed copy of a typewritten draft
  - Asia
    - Many Asias and Asian unity, 1954-1956
    - Marxism in, 1951-1959 (Box 2.)
    - Mind of, 1955-1959
  - Australian Institute of International Affairs
    - Bulletins, 1943-1946
    - Correspondence, 1940-1946
  - Austria, 1934-1938
  - Barnes, Joseph, clippings of articles on the Soviet Union for the New York Herald Tribune1939
  - Blumenthal, "The Soviet Union and The United Nations," n.d. Mimeographed copy of a typewritten draft
  - Bricker Amendment, 1952-1954 (Box 3.)
  - Cartoons, 1948
  - Central Europe, 1940-1941
  - Chamberlin, William Henry
    - "Manchukuo--Japan's Imperialistic Venture," clippings of a series of 6 articles for the Christian Science Monitor1936
    - "Russia--without Benefit of Censor," clippings of a series of 18 articles for the Christian Science Monitor1934
  - China
    - General, 1946-1962
    - Communism in, 1953, 1957-1958
    - Empire and colonies, 1958
    - Politics
    - Sinkiang, 1935-1945
  - Colonialism, 1949-1953 (Box 4.)
  - Comintern (3rd International), 1935-1939, 1947
  - Communism abroad, 1929-1941
  - Conference on the Transformation of Russian Society since 1861, April 25-27, 1958
  - Courts, 1937
  - Cuba, 1959-1963
  - Czechoslovakia, 1936-1940
  - Democracy, Soviet-American ideas of, 1933-1947
  - Duranty, Walter and Harold Denny, clippings of articles on the Soviet Union, 1930-1940 (Box 5.)
  - Education, 1951-1952 (Box 6.)
  - Educational Committee to Halt Atomic Weapons Spread, 1966
  - Estonia - relations with Russia, 1929
  - Far East, 1934-1939
  - Fascism, 1937-1939
  - Finland
    - General, 1918-1919, 1931-1941
      - 1918-1919
      - 1931-1938 (Box 7.)
      - 1939
      - 1940
        - January-March
        - March-October
    - Allies and the German king, 1918
    - Chronology (Box 8.)
    - Communist activities in, 1929
    - Economic and social conditions, 1929
    - Famine relief, 1918-1923
      - General
      - Children
      - Russian refugees
    - Foreign policy, 1929
    - German intervention and the Terror, 1918
    - Karelia, ca. 1921-1928 (information on Karelia enclosed in envelope addressed to Herbert Hoover from the Finnish Legation)
    - Maps and photographs
    - Relations with Russia, 1929
    - Miscellany
  - Foreign - misc., 1935-1940
  - France, 1935-1940
  - Freund, H. A.
  - Freund, H. A. (Box 9.)
    - Lectures on the Soviet Union, 1943-1946
      - Typewritten and handwritten drafts, typewritten mimeographed copies
    - Pamphlets (printed copies)
      - "Handelsrecht und Handels-Regulierung in der Sowjetunion (Business Rights and Government Influence in the Soviet Union)," 1928
      - "Juristiche Ubersicht (Jurisprudence)," 1932
      - "L'Avenir du Droit Civil dans l'Union Sovietique (Concerning Civil Rights in the Soviet Union)," 1937
      - "L'Etat sovietique et la Statut de ses Representations commerciales (The Soviet State and its Commercial Representation Statute)," 1934
      - "Soviet Law under 'Stalinism'," 1939
      - "Zasada Domicylu W Nowym Lotewskim Prawie Miedzynarodowym," (The Right of Domicile in the New Latvian International Law)," 1938
    - Radio broadcasts, 1946
  - Germany, 1935-1939
  - Great Britain, 1936-1939 (Box 10.)
  - Greece, 1936-1938
  - Herbert Hoover Presidential Library, 1970-1974
  - History, 1935-1938, 1941-1945
  - Hoover (Herbert) and the American Relief Admnistration, 1925
  - House Committee on Un-American Activities. Contempt of Congress against Dr. Jeremiah Standler and Mrs. Yolanda Hall, 1966
  - Hungary, 1936-1940
  - Indonesia, 1945-1955
  - Internationale Vereinigung fuer Rechts-und Wirtschaftsphilosophie (International Organization for Rights and Scientific Philosophy) (Box 11.)
  - Islam, 1950-1956
  - Israel, 1948-1958
  - Italy, 1935-1940
  - Japan, 1945-1952
  - Kelly, Fred C., "Notes from a Russian Diary," clippings of a series of articles for the New York Herald Tribune1933.
  - Knickerbocker, H. R., "Fighting the Red Trade Menace," clippings of a series of 24 articles for the New York Evening Post1930-1931
  - Korea, 1948-1950
  - Latvia, 1940
  - Lithuania, 1929, 1938-1940
  - Madison, Bernice, "Organization of Welfare Services in Pre- and Post-Revolutionary Russia, 1861-1957," n.d. Typewritten draft
  - Malaya, 1957
  - Manchurian Crisis, 1931
  - Mason, John Brown, Research Resources; Annotated Guide to the Social Sciences, 1966. Mimeographed typewritten copy (Box 12.)
  - Micronesia, 1967-1969
  - Middle East, 1950-1958
  - National Council for Civic Responsibility, 1964-1966
  - Nazi-Soviet relations, 1939-1941, 1948
  - Neutralism, 1955
  - New Deal, 1935-1936
  - Newman, Joseph, "Russia Uncensored," clippings of a series of articles for the New York Herald Tribune1949
  - Peace, 1936-1942 (Box 13.)
  - Peace and Plenty - science and the post-war world, 1941-1942
  - "Peaceful Change in Modern Society," conference presented by the Hoover Institution on its 50th anniversary, 1969
  - Philippines, 1941
  - Poland, 1935-1953
  - RADIR project - Revolution, 1943-1948
  - Relief - Europe, 1941
  - Revolution, general, 1931-1955
  - Rhineland crisis, 1936
  - Rumania, 1937-1940
  - Russia (Imperial), 1942-1957
  - San Francisco Conference, 1944-1945 (Box 14.)
    - General
    - Amendments
    - British Commonwealth
    - Chapultapec Conference
    - Charter text
    - Closing of conference
    - Countries (individual)
    - Delegates (Box 15.)
    - Dumbarton Oaks
    - Economic and social cooperation
    - Educational and cultural cooperation
    - Large vs. small states
    - Latin America (Box 16.)
    - Membership
    - Organization
    - Personnel
    - Poland
    - Progress
    - Regions
    - Representation (Box 17.)
    - Rights
    - Soviet Union
    - Stassen, Harold
    - Syria - Lebanon
    - Trusteeships
    - Veto
    - Voting
    - Working papers
    - World court (Box 18.)
    - Yalta
    - Yugoslavia
  - Schapiro, Leonard, The Communist Party of the Soviet Union mimeographed copy of a typewritten draft of chapters 6-14, n.d.
  - School of Naval Administration, schedules and lists of guest speakers, 1946-1947
  - Science and democracy, 1933-1946
  - Science and revolution, 1942-1950
  - Seminar on Peace Settlement, Hoover Library, 1941
  - Sian, 1936 (Box 19.)
  - Soviet Union
    - General, 1917-1918, 1930-1949
    - General (Box 20.)
    - Armed Forces, 1944-1948
    - Asia and, 1944-1945
    - Atomic energy, 1945-1947
    - Chronology (1936-1940)
    - Communist Party of the Soviet Union (C.P.S.U.) Twentieth Congress of, 1956
    - Constitution, elections, and Supreme Soviet, 1936-1940, 1945 (Box 21.)
    - Culture, 1943-1951
    - Daily life, 1945-1949
    - Economy, 1945-1952
    - Education, 1947-1951
    - Five-Year Plan, 1928-1933 (Box 22.)
    - Foreign relations, 1930-1940
      - General, 1932-1940
      - Collective security, 1933-1939 (Box 23.)
      - Far East, 1930-1940
    - Historiography, 1946-1951
    - Industry, invention, and exploration, 1935-1938
    - Law, 1932-1938, 1947-1949
    - Leaders, 1945-1951 (Box 24.)
    - Nationality policy, 1943-1951
    - Newspapers (copies of Pravda and Izvestia), 1946-1947
    - Post-war, 1946-1950
    - Propaganda, 1947-1949
    - Purges, 1934-1937
    - Religion
      - 1930-1938
      - 1948 (Box 25.)
    - U.S. opinion of, 1944-1947
    - War and peace, 1937-1940
    - Workers, 1932-1940
    - World War II, 1939-1949
  - Spain
    - General, 1956
    - Civil war
      - 1936
        - July-December
        - September-November
      - 1937 (Box 26.)
        - January
        - January-April
        - April-July
        - August-September
        - October-December
      - 1938 (Box 27.)
        - February
        - March
        - April
        - May
        - June
        - July
        - August-December
      - 1939-1940
  - Stalin, Joseph, 1956-1962 (Box 28.)
  - Sudeten crisis, 1938
  - Suez, 1956
  - Trotsky, Leon, Stalin: An Appraisal of the Man and His Influence, translated by Charles Malamuth, 1941. Typewritten carbon copy of changes made in galley copy.
  - Trust territories, 1949-1950
  - Turkey, 1939
  - Ukraine, 1939-1940
  - United States
    - Communism in, 1928-1937, 1939-1940
      - 1928-1937
      - 1939-1940
    - Constitution, 1952-1954
    - Finns in, 1918-1927
    - Labor - strikes and organizations, 1935-1937
    - Liberalism, anti-liberalism, fascism, 1937-1940
    - Radicalism, 1933-1941, 1967
    - Revolution in, 1948-1949
    - War Policy of, 1935-1940 (Box 30.)
  - World War II, Communists in, 1939-1941
  - Yalta Conference - official record, 1955
- Speeches and Writings, 1926 (Box No. 30.)
  Books and articles, arranged alphabetically by title.
  - "The Beginning of the 'Third Period', 1928-1929," n.d. Typewritten draft, with typewritten carbon copies of appended documents (Box 30.)
  - "The Character of American Participation in Euoropean Affairs since the War," 1926. Printed copy.
  - "History of Relief," 1926. Article prepared for the Encyclopaedia Britannica. Typewritten draft.
- Miscellany (Box No. 31-36.)
  Card catalogs, microfilm and notes, arranged as listed.
  - Card catalogues (Box 31.)
    - Chronology of historical events (for 1899-1939)
    - Research notes, alphabetized by subject (Box 32-33.)
  - Microfilm (Box 34.)
    - Partiinoe Stroitel'stvo - Zhurnal Tsentral'nogo Komiteta Vsesoiuznoi Kommunisticheskoi Partii (Party Structure - Journal of the Central Committee
      - Reel No. 1. 1929-1930
      - Reel No. 2. 1931
      - Reel No. 3. 1932-1933
      - Reel No. 4. 1933-1934
      - Reel No. 5. 1935-1936
  - Notes (Box 35-36.)
- Audio-Visual File
  Includes one record, photographs, and an album.
  - Sound recording of radio newscast, 30 August 1946 (Folder Record Cabinet)
    Use copy reference number: xx235_a_0002811
    Headline Edition. Newscast. August 30, 1946. Council of Foreign Ministers. Paris Peace Conference. Interview with Dr. Harold Fisher, Director of the School of Naval Administration, Stanford, Calif. 1 disc
  - 1 print of Harold H. Fisher with Army officers, circa 1946-1947 (Folder A)
  - 3 prints of paintings depicting the famine in Soviet Russia, plus 3 negatives, 1918-1923 (Folder B)
  - 1 framed print of Herbert C. and Lou Henry Hoover (autographed), undated (Folder C)
  - 1 mounted print of a painting of Herbert C. Hoover (autographed), 1944 (Folder mD)
  - 5 prints of Harold H. Fisher and others; 2 prints of unidentified groups, undated (Folder E)
  - 1 photograph album of a conference, 1954 (Folder fF)
- Biographical Card File (Box No. 37-59.)
  Biographical notes, relating mainly to persons figuring in the Russian Revolution, arranged alphabetically.
  - A (Box 37.)
  - B-Bod (Box 38.)
  - Bog-Ca (Box 39.)
  - Ce-Da (Box 40.)
  - De-E (Box 41.)
  - F-Gi (Box 42.)
  - Gl-Gz (Box 43.)
  - H-I (Box 44.)
  - J-Kh (Box 45.)
  - Ki-Ks (Box 46.)
  - Ku-Li (Box 47.)
  - Ll-Maz (Box 48.)
  - Mc-Mz (Box 49.)
  - N-O (Box 50.)
  - P-Poz (Box 51.)
  - Pr-Roz (Box 52.)
  - Ru-Se (Box 53.)
  - Sh-Sr (Box 54.)
  - St-Te (Box 55.)
  - Th-Van (Box 56.)
  - Var-W (Box 57.)
  - X-Z (Box 58.)
  - Miscellany (Box 59.)
- Miscellaneous Biographical Card File. (Box No. 60.)
  Biographical notes, unarranged.
  - Miscellaneous Biographical Card File (Box 60.)
- Lenin's Sochineniia Biographical Card File (Box No. 61-63.)
  Index to persons mentioned in the Sochneniia of V. I. Lenin, arranged alphabetically.
  - A-Ke (Box 61.)
  - Kh-Sh (Box 62.)
  - Si-Z (Box 63.)
- Bibliographical Card File (Box No. 64-68.)
  Bibliographical references to topics mainly associated with the Russian Revolution, unarranged.
  - Biographical Card File (Box 64-68.)
- Biographical Card File II. (Box No. 69-74)
  - A-C (Box 69.)
  - D-H (Box 70.)
  - I-L (Box 71.)
  - M-Q (Box 72.)
  - R-S (Box 73.)
  - T-Z (Box 74.)
- Newspaper Card File. (Box No. 75-77.)
  Notes relating to newspapers and other periodicals, mainly associated with the Russian Revolution, arranged alphabetically.
  - A-Ko (Box 75.)
  - Kr-Sot (Box 76.)
  - Sov-Z (Box 77.)